Guide to the James Jesse Strang Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James Jesse Strang papers
1829-1870
WA MSS S-186-189
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.75
(4 boxes)
The collection contains letters to and from James Jesse Strang and some third party correspondence. There is a meteorological journal from Beaver Island, Michigan, which includes notes on the fishes and shells of the area, Strang's diary covering 1831-1836, and documents of the Order of the Illuminati.
Strang, James Jesse, 1813-1856
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Unspecified, please consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 6: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Associated Materials
James Jesse Strang Collection, WA MSS 447
Scope and Contents
James Jesse Strang (1813-1856), was a founder of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter Day Saints (Strangite). The collection contains letters to and from James Jesse Strang and some third party correspondence. There is also a meterological journal from Beaver Island, Michigan, which includes notes on the fishes and shells of the area, Strang's diary covering 1831-1836, and documents of the Order of the Illuminati.
Mormons -- Michigan; Beaver Island (Mich.); Diaries -- United States; Losee, Myraette A. Strang, 1818-; Strang, James Jesse, 1813-1856; Strang, Mary Perce; Tucker, C.; Order of the Illuminati
- Journal (WA MSS S-186)
  - Strang, James Jesse. Meteorological Journal, St. James [Mich.], 1850-1856 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Records cover Dec 1850 - July 1851, Sep 1852 - May 1856. Also includes "Fishes of Beaver Island Harbour", "Shells and shell-fish" and "Vibrations of mercury in the thermometer".
- Strang Letterbook (WA MSS S-187)
  The numbers to the left of the description refer to letter number; documents are bound in the contemporary letterbook in no discernable order. All letters are to James Jesse Strang unless otherwise specified.
  - Rathbone, A. D. ALS. Forestville [N.Y]., 1836 Jul 14 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General Law Agency, G. J. Grosvenor. Printed form., [after 1840] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS. Silver Creek [N.Y]., 1836 Jun 12 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Messenger, Westfield [N.Y]. Printed form., 1842 Mar 16 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hazelton, Benjamin. ALS. Mason Center, N.Y., 1839 Aug 16 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Johnson, L., P.M. ALS. Gerry P.O., Chautauqua Co., N.Y., 1839 Sep 28 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Daughter "A L" [Almira L]. ALS to "Dear Cousin Mary" & James J. Strang. Brantford [Canada]., 1842 Feb 20 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Strang, Amaziah. ALS. Jamestown [N.Y]., 1837 Mar 6 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Strang, Francis. ALS. Westfield Tiogra Co., Pa., 1841 May 14 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Strang, Gabriel. ALS. Richmond, Ind., 1840 Sep 18 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Post Office Dept., Amos Kendall. DS. Printed form., 1838 Dec 27 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Commission of postmaster at Ellington.
  - Strang, G[abriel]. ALS to James J. Strang & wife. Richmond, Ind., l841 Jan 12 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Strang, G[abriel]. ALS. Perington., 1840 Mar 3 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS (copy) to E. Harman. Ellington [N.Y]., 1841 Jul 6 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Clark, Lot. ALS. Dunkirk [N.Y.], 1841 Aug 30 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS (draft) to Miss W[ealthy] Smith. Clear Creek [N.Y]., 1836 Sep 10 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Harman & Wilson. ALS., [1841 Jul] (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS. Chautauqua., 1841 Aug 27 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Seaver, William A. ALS. Batavia [N.Y]., 1841 Jun 30 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - James J. Strang to "Dear Father" [Clement Strang]. Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Mar 12 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Prentiss, Russell. ALS. Saint Louis, Mo. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS., 1841 Jul 18 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Post Office Dept: Amos Kendall. Printed form., 1839 Mar 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Dear Ben" [Benjamin Hazelton]. Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Feb 23 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Smith, William. ALS. Mayville, N.Y., 1841 Aug 23 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Wilson & Company. Ellington, N.Y., 1841 Jan 25 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Post Office Dept: Rob. Johnston, 2nd Asst. P.M. Gen. Printed form., 1838 Nov 24 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to John N. James (copy)., 1835 Dec 23 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS (copy) to C. Tucker. Ellington, N.Y., 1838 Apr 4 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Post Office Dept: Amos Kendall. ALS., 1840 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Hand-written, "ditto machine".
  - Perce, W. L. ALS., 1841 Jun 27 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "H N E P" [Mrs. Strang's Brother Perce] to Mrs. James J. Strang., [n.y.] Mar 24 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to B[enjamin] Hazelton. Ellington, N.Y., 1841 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Strang, Gabriel. ALS. South Charleston, O., 1842 Mar 27 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "B.C.P" and Ellen Perce. ALS. Bloomfield., 1841 Jul 16 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Heading is "My dear Niece".
  - "Jamie" [James J. Strang] to "Dear Mary" [Mrs. Mary Perce Strang]. Ellington, N.Y., 1847 Feb 26 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to John W. James., 1836 Jun 16 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - George W. Little. Cherry Valley, N.Y., 1842 Jan 15 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Aldrich, Hazen. ALS. Stanley Corners, N.Y., 1831 Sep 16 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Perce, Benjamin C. ALS. Cherry Creek, N.Y., 1842 Jul 12 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Boston Notion: George Roberts. Printed form., 1841 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang. Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Mar (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Boston Notion. Printed form, mentioned in letter 41., 1841 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Eve[ning] Journal: Thomas White & W. H. Corbin. ALS. Albany., 1842 Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Strang, Mary (Perce). ALS. N.Y., 1837 Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Strang, Francis. ALS., 1841 Dec 10 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Strang, James, ALS. Schuylerville, N.Y., 1835 Jul 21 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Hinckley, I. G. [Mayville]. ALS., 1842 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Tucker, C. ALS. Fredonia, N.Y., 1842 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Hazeltine, A. ALS. Jamestown, N.Y., 1842 May 21 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Smith, A. ALS. Westfield, N.Y., 1841 Mar 29 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Badger, J. ALS. Honeoye Falls, N.Y., 1839 Jun 19 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - James, John N. ALS. New York., 1836 Mar 8 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Rathbone, A. D. ALS. Grand Rapids, Mich., 1840 Jan 6 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Perce, Ellen. ALS to "My Dear Niece" [Mary Perce Strang]., 1840 Jun 28 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Peacock, William W. ALS. Mayville, N.Y., 1840 Dec 10 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Office of Treasurer, E. Whittlesey, Auditor. Printed form., 1841 Nov 10 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Manly James. Silver Creek, N.Y., 1836 Jun 12 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to C. Tucker. Ellington, N.Y., 1839 Nov 1 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Parker, Charles. ALS. Ashville, N.Y., 1840 Aug 3 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Perce, W. L. [father]. ALS., 1838 Jul 1 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Strang, James. ALS to "Mr. Perce" [Mary's father]. Clear Creek., 1836 Sep 22 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Perce, W. L. [father]. ALS., 1836 Oct 10 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Sister", E. H. Perce. Mayville, N.Y., 1838 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Tucker, C. ALS., 1838 May 21 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Post Office Department: C. A. Wickliffe [in print], Post Master General. Printed form., 1842 Jan 24 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Post Office Dept. Blank printed form., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Post Office Dept.: C. A. Wickliffe [in print], Post Master General. Printed form., 1841 Nov 1 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Tucker, C. ALS., 1839 Sep 8 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Dear Parents" [Perce family]., 1838 Jan 25 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Strang, Gilbert [Francis Strang]. ALS., 1842 Sep 16 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Dear Parents & Sister" [Perce Family]. Ellington Center, N.Y., 1837 Feb 12 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Willing, Richard. ALS. N.p., 1839 Nov 26 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Winchester. E. ALS. Fredonia, N.Y., 1840 Oct 24 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Central Comm. [political]. Printed form with note in Strang's hand on it., 1840 Oct 19 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Peacock, William W. ALS. Mayville, N.Y., 1840 Nov 10 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Strang, Francis. ALS., 1841 July 7 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - LaHatt, Charles H. ALS. Girard, Ala., 1841 Aug 8 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Seward, B. J. ALS. Westfield, N.Y., 1839 Apr 1 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Hughes, Harriet. ALS. Marseilles, N.Y., 1841 Mar 14 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Bowen & McManus Co. ALS Strang. N.Y., 1842 Jan 24 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Perce, Benjamin C. ALS Strang. Burlington., 1842 Jan 27 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Gibbs, Anson. ALS. N.p., 1840 Jun 27 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Treasury Dept; Auditor signed, E. Whittlesey. Printed form., 1841 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary P. Strang. Clear Creek, N.Y., 1837 Jan 20 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Post Office Dept., signed George Hitt, agent. ALS. N.Y., 1842 Jan 28 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang. Clear Creek, N.Y., 1837 Jan 13 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Signed by clerk Jno. Robertson, Jr. ALS. Ohio River., 1841 May 9 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Strang, Mary (Perce). ALS. Ellicottville, N.Y., 1837 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Democratic Party, Comm. of Correspondence. Printed form., 1840 Feb 8 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Respected Friend". Clear Creek, N.Y., 1836 Aug 29 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Strang, Mary (Perce). ALS., Winter, 1836-7 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Amaziah Strang. Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Amaziah Strang. Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Apr 3 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang. Clear Creek, N.Y., 1836 Dec 5 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Strang, Mary (Perce). ALS. Little Valley., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang., 1837 Apr 13 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Treasury Dept., Auditor's Office: signed E. Whittlesey. Printed form., 1841 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang. Clear Creek, N.Y., 1835 Dec 5 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - C.H. Read Company. ALS to W.T. Norris [Postmaster at Ellington]. Troy, N.Y., 1839 May 14 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang. Ellington Center, N.Y., 1837 Apr 4 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Strang, Francis. ALS. Westfield, N.Y., 1841 Jul 2 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang., 1837 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Patchin, A. D. ALS., 1839 Sep 28 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Very dear Sister" [H. N. Perce]. Ellicottville., 1837 Feb 18 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Myraette. Clear Creek, N.Y., 1836 Jul 26 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Hazeltine, Abner. ALS. Jamestown, N.Y., 1834 Oct 29 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Hazeltine, Abner. ALS. Washington., 1835 Jan 30 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Amanda". Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Feb 25 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS (copy) to Mr. Fuller. Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS (copy) to Peter L. Fraser. Clear Creek, N.Y., 183-? Jun 27 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Dear Ellen". N.p., 1837 Feb 23 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Strang, Mary (Perce). ALS. Ellicottville, N.Y.., 1837 Jan 14 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Strang, James. ALS. Schuylerville, N.Y., 1829 Nov 25 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - James, Manly. ALS. New York City, N.Y., 1835 Nov 25 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Strang, Mary (Perce). ALS. Ellicottville, N.Y., 1837 Feb 21 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Edwards, Charles [Texas Land Co.]. ALS to James J. Strang and Ward., 1834 Nov 17 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - Rathbone, A. D. ALS. N.p., [n.y.] Jan 8 (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Parker, Charles. ALS. Ashville, N.Y., 1840 Feb 6 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Post Office Dept: signed M. Paine, agent. ALS., 1840 Jun 20 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Perce, L. [Mary's mother]. ALS to James J. & Mary P. Strang. N.p., 1838 Feb 23 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Perce, W. L. [on same sheet as above letter]. ALS to James J. & Mary P. Strang. N.p., 1840 Feb 23 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Democratic Party. "To the Democratic Electors of the State of N. York". Printed form., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to W. L. Perce., 1837 Jul 2 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - R. J. Hilton [Lawyer in Albany]. Printed form., 18[?] Aug (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Hughes, Harriet & Perce, L. (Mrs.). ALS to Mary Perce Strang ["Dear Sis"]., 1840 Sep 20 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang. Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Feb 20 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - Strang, Amaziah. ALS. Leon Center, N.Y., 1839 Oct 28 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - Strang, Amaziah. ALS. Leon Center, N.Y., 1840 Apr 10 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Strang, Amaziah. ALS. Leon Center, N.Y., 1840 Apr 4 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Strang, G. [Gabriel]. ALS. N.Y., 1840 Jun 1 (Box 2, Folder 131)
  - Strang. Gabriel. ALS. South Bloomfield Picaway County, Ohio., 1840 Jul 19 (Box 2, Folder 132)
  - Strang, Amaziah. ALS. Leon Center, N.Y., 1839 Aug 16 (Box 2, Folder 133)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS. Chautauque, N.Y., 1841 Apr 22 (Box 2, Folder 134)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS. Chautauque, N.Y., 1840 May 16 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS. Chautauque, N.Y., 1837 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 136)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS. Chautauque, N.Y., 1838 Oct 25 (Box 2, Folder 137)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS. Chautauque, N.Y., 1840 Jan 21 (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS to Mary Perce Strang. Chautauque, N.Y., 1840 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 139)
  - Strang, David. ALS. Hanover, N.Y., 1837 Jan 31 (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - James, John N. ALS. Jamesville, N.Y., 1839 Jul 22 (Box 2, Folder 141)
  - James, Manly. ALS. Jamesville, N.Y., 1839 Jul 6 (Box 2, Folder 142)
  - Little, George W. ALS. Cherry Valley, N.Y., 1840 Oct 4 (Box 2, Folder 143)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS. Chautauque, N.Y., 1840 Mar 27 (Box 2, Folder 144)
  - Losee, Myraette A. (Strang). ALS. Chautauque, N.Y., 1840 Apr 10 (Box 2, Folder 145)
  - Jones, William. ALS. Chicago, Ill., 1841 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 146)
  - James, John N. ALS. N.Y., 1840 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 147)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Mr. James", draft. Mayville, N.Y., 1837 Nov 17 (Box 2, Folder 148)
  - James, John W. ALS. N.Y., 1840 Mar 19 (Box 2, Folder 149)
  - Strope, M. ALS to "Editors of the Randolph Herald., 1843 Mar 31 (Box 2, Folder 150)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Dear Father" [Clement Strang]. Ellington, N.Y., 1837 Apr 18 (Box 2, Folder 151)
  - Kershaw, John. ALS. Millersburg, N.Y., 1838 Dec 26 (Box 2, Folder 152)
  - James, Jonathan. ALS to Jesse Brooks. Cherry Creek, N.Y., 1837 Dec 10 (Box 2, Folder 153)
  - James, John N. ALS. N.Y., 1839 Dec 25 (Box 2, Folder 154)
  - James, John N. ALS. N.Y., 1839 Mar 8 (Box 2, Folder 155)
  - Briggs, John R. ALS. Westfield, N.Y., 1843 Mar 16 (Box 2, Folder 156)
  - Strang, Ira. ALS. Stillwater, N.Y., 1841 Mar 28 (Box 2, Folder 157)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to M. Strope. Randolph., 1843 Apr 9 (Box 2, Folder 158)
  - Strang, A. [Amaziah]. ALS. Leon Center, N.Y., 1841 Jan 23 (Box 2, Folder 159)
  - Warren, E. F. ALS. Jamestown, N.Y., 1843 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 160)
  - Salisbury, Manchester & Co. Printed form., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 161)
  - Strang, G. [Gabriel]. ALS., 1841 Feb 18 (Box 2, Folder 162)
  - Erie County Republican General Corresponding Committee [Buffalo, N.Y]. Printed form., 1843 Mar 13 (Box 2, Folder 163)
  - O'Reilly, H. ALS. N.p., 1842 Feb 12 (Box 2, Folder 164)
  - Waith, William. ALS. Ellington, N.Y., 1843 Apr 19 (Box 2, Folder 165)
  - Citizens of Ellington. ALS (draft) "To the Post Master General of the United States". Ellington, N.Y., 1838 Nov 6 (Box 2, Folder 166)
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to Mary Perce Strang. Mayville., 1841 Oct 15 (Box 2, Folder 167)
  - Strang, G. [Gabriel]. ALS. Richmond, Ind., 1840 Nov 19 (Box 2, Folder 168)
  - Foote, E. T. ALS. Jamestown, N.Y., 1840 Jul (Box 2, Folder 169)
    "Friday Morning."
  - Strang, James Jesse. ALS to "Sir", draft. N.p., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 170)
    Concerning post office business.
- Diary (WA MSS S-188)
  - Strang, James Jesse. Diary., 1831-1836 (Box 3–4)
    Some pages missing; most mutilated. Partly in cipher. Includes 15 leaves listed in Withington, Western Americana Manuscripts, 447.
    Photostatic copy & typescript available for general use. For original, see: Restricted Fragile Papers.
- Order of the Illuminati Covenant (WA MSS S-189)
  - Order of the Illuminati. Covenant rituals and lists of members., 1850-1870 (Box 5)
    The covenant of the secret order within the Strangite Mormon church, signed by the members, and lists of members added up to 1870.
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 3 (WA MSS S-188) (Box 6)